A Guide to the Juanita White Papers, 1970-1997
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Juanita White Papers, 1970-1997
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M354
2.4 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Juanita White of Richmond, Virginia, on 26 October 2005.
Biographical Information
Juanita White was a founding member of the Richmond branch of the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.). As a member of N.O.W. she served as the local officer of reproductive rights. In 1983 she was the branch's delegate to the National N.O.W. Conference. Around this time she also volunteered as the local branch newsletter editor. During the late 1970's and early 1980's, Juanita White also participated in the activities of the E.R.A. Ratification Council. Juanita White resides in Richmond with her husband.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1970-1997, of Juanita White of Richmond, Virginia, principally consisting of personal files, clippings, correspondence, newsletters, personal daybooks, photographs, and a scrapbook. Materials generally concern her work with women's activist organizations but some materials pertain to her personal life and the life and art of Eleanor Appel Lawrence. There is extensive information regarding the Richmond branch of the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.), and the Richmond branch of the Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council.
Arrangement
Arranged in eight series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1970-1997
Series II. Personal Files, 1975-1991
Series III. National Organization for Women Files, 1970-1977
Series IV. Equal Rights Amendment Files, 1972-1977
Series V. Other Organiations' Publications, 1974-1979, 1997
Series VI. Clippings, 1974-1979
Series VII. Photographs, n.d.
Series VIII. Feminist Music, n.d.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1970-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Correspondence includes a letter, 23 November 1970, from Zelda K. Nordlinger of the Women's Liberation Front in Richmond, Virginia, to Wilma Scott Heide, chairperson of the National Organization for Women in Pennsylvania concerning starting a Richmond branch of N.O.W.; letter, 11 April 1977, from Juanita B. White in Richmond to Evelyn Marr Glazier of the Richmond ERA Ratification Council complaining of the recent divisive acts of the organization; a letter, 22 September 1978, from Harry F. Byrd, Jr., to Juanita B. White concerning his views on the extending of the deadline to accept the Constitutional Amendment; letter, 28 December 1978, from Benjamin Lambert, III, stating that he agrees that the Equal Rights Amendment issue should come to the House floor for a vote; and letter, 11 December 1978, from James S. Christian, Jr., to Juanita White concerning his views on the Equal Rights Amendment.
  Arranged chronologically within the folder.
- Personal Files, 1975-1991 (Box 1, Folders 2-15)
  Contains daybooks, 1975-1986, of Juanita White including dates and notes concerning women's activist organization meetings. There is also a scrapbook, 1975-1991, containing newspaper clippings, photos, correspondence, and N.O.W. newsletters related to women's organizations and women's activists in Richmond; and a copy of "You, Too, Can Sell!" by Eleanor Appel (Lawrence). Scrapbook has been disassembled in order to address preservation issues.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Daybook, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Daybook, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daybook, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Daybook, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Daybook, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Daybook, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Daybook, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Daybook, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Daybook, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Daybook, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fundraising pledge card, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous feminist documents, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1975-1991, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "You, Too, Can Sell," by Eleanor Appel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- National Organization for Women Files, 1970-1977 (Boxes 1-2, Folders 16-18b, 1)
  Comprises N.O.W. national organization newsletters, 1974-1977; N.O.W. Richmond branch newsletters, 1976-1977, 1982-1983; Richmond branch history, ca. 1974; and National Conference programs and schedule, 1975, 1982. There are also copies of the National N.O.W. Times, the official journal of N.O.W., 1978-1979.
  - National Conference programs and schedule, 1975, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National N.O.W. Times, February 1978-August 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National organization newsletters, November 1974-April 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16a)
  - Richmond branch Equality Day flyer, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Richmond branch history, ca. 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Richmond branch newsletters, June 1976-May 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18a)
  - Richmond branch newsletters, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18b)
- Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council Files, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Consists of Federal and state legal documents, correspondence, and publications concerning the Equal Rights Amendment. Also contains a copy of the Report of the Task Force on the Effect of Ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment on the Law of Virginia, n.d., submitted by the Subcommittee on the Equal Rights Amendment, Joint Committee on Privileges and Elections; a copy of the Equal Rights Amendment Supporter's Handbook, September 1974; and newsletters, minutes, and meeting announcement, 1976-1977, of the Richmond ERA Ratification Council.
- Other Organizations' Publications, 1974-1979, 1997 (Boxes 1-2, Folders 20-20a, 2-3)
  Principally consists of publications from other national feminist organizations. There are also copies of the The Blue Lantern: a New Woman's Journal, ca. 1970's, Pandora: a Washington Women's Journal, 1978, and the Richmond-area Woman Activist newsletter, August 1976.
  - The Blue Lantern: a New Woman's Journal, ca. 1970's (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1974-1979, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pandora: a Washington Women's Journal, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Woman Activist newsletter, August 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20a)
- Clippings, 1974-1979, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Comprises clippings, 1974-1979, and n.d. concerning feminist organizations and activists, particularly N.O.W. and its members in Richmond.
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Contains photographs of sculptures by Eleanor Lawrence and housed at the Unitarian Church in Richmond, Virginia.
- Feminist Music, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Contains a copy of Leave the Breads a Burning!, feminist music by the Arlington Street Women's Chorus copyright 1974.